[Music]
just as the pandemic was starting
Daniel Thorson went into a 75 day silent
retreat but the monastic academy in
Vermont he came out into a postcode
world and straight into the New York
Times interviews around the globe and
became a viral tik-tok hit in China but
there's an even more interesting story
behind it
because four years before the pandemic
exposed how fragile our systems were
Daniel was exploring exactly these
questions of existential risk through
the emerged podcast so I wanted to see
what he was making of the experience you
read the New York Times article about me
then was subsequently contacted by like
I'm probably like a dozen or more
different news agencies around the world
like I did a radio interview in
Australia and in in London and Ireland
and and then I definitely the most I
guess the main feeling I feel is
amusement right now it's very surreal to
come off of asylum a 75 day silent
retreat and be like thrust into the blue
church media machine and kind of just
digested and taken for a ride so yeah
it's it's surreal yeah it's just the
juxtaposition it's like you deliberately
did absolutely nothing or very little
for 75 days and that's become incredibly
newsworthy for everyone that's the
strangest thing is that that would be at
all newsworthy but I think it actually
it reflects how sort of significant
people think that the last two months
were that they want to see a reflection
of themselves in me who didn't
participate in it and so it's funny
because people are asking me like well
what was it like what's it like for you
but really I I think they really want me
to ask them what it was like for
hmm you know cuz I didn't like you know
I didn't go through it and I'm almost
having to read a history of it yeah
there's been these videos that have gone
pretty viral of people sort of talking
to their pre lockdown selves like how
would it be I saw one of those I think
that's really insightful you are kind of
the pre lockdown self although I was
under lockdown you know it was voluntary
but I was under lockdown I just didn't
have all the social media feeds and the
news of the information coming at me but
I knew I you know I the other thing is
that I think I posted an ironic tweet
and and it was I'm back from 75 days in
silence did I miss anything and of
course like I knew that there was a
pandemic right so if obviously I I
obviously knew and you can actually look
like three more tweets down in my
timeline to see me asking about the
impact the known impacts of kovat on
people of certain age ranges and how to
protect against it as the community so
there are now newsagent and so this has
been really interesting to see how
things get distorted by the news media
right so there then portraying me as if
I'm this like I had no clue that this
was happening I was just completely in
the dark which is so clearly not true
and you would just have to do an iota of
research to find that out you know yeah
but that's why I find the whole thing so
astonishing and is because and I don't
think the New York Times are to have got
there and probably none of the other
news piece has got there either is
because you'd been going into
existential risk you've been doing a
real deep dive into exactly all of these
topics that are now front and center of
everyone's mind which is what I find
astonishing about this whole situations
you've come out and also the fact that
we talked about kind of you feeling that
you come to the end of that exploration
you were sort of like I can not sure
where I go next with this yeah like that
deeper level of on some level you'd gone
as deeply as anyone I think
into understanding the the sort of how
how badly wrong our source code had gone
and how fragile our society was I mean
that's what I I'm really interested in
was there a sense of recognition when
you came out like her this is what I was
maybe picking up towards the end of the
exploration with the podcast recognition
yeah it's something like I wasn't
surprised I wasn't surprised and I I
don't want to say I felt vindicated but
I felt like more confident in the
decisions I made about how I'm living my
life because I have I have intentionally
chosen to live in a way that I think
takes into account as you say the kind
of buggy source code of our planetary
system and so because I live in that way
this actually the whole pandemic whether
or not I was in solitary retreat
wouldn't have been as massive and impact
because I live in community you know we
cook for each other we entertain each
other we cut each other's hair you know
and so I wouldn't have been isolated in
the way that so many folks were and
furthermore I wouldn't have I mean I
wouldn't have lost my job all these
things would have been sort of I've
already lost my job I've already lost my
life I've already walked down the hill
of collapse to a large degree my life is
incredibly simple and so you know as
people begin to grieve the loss of the
world
they thought they could depend on I've
done that I've been doing that for years
and
so like I feel kind of business as usual
it's amazing to to watch the planet go
through this and to be here for it but
it's not surprising and what when you
save the planet go through this what is
your frame yeah my model is just that
there's a phase shift systems collapse a
movement into a time between worlds as
Zack Stein puts it and that there's now
an acceleration of that seemingly due to
the pandemic and second and third order
effects from that and then those weaving
back into the complicated complex system
so I mean so that's what it is is it's a
dissolution it's a dissolution it's a
revealing as you say it's an apocalypse
and I think that can be quite beautiful
or it can be horrible depends on how we
participate with it and whether we've
been lying to ourselves up until this
point or how much we've been lying to
ourselves until this point assume you
have exactly we've all been lying to
ourselves to some degree indeed indeed
yeah thank you I think I think let's
recap the word apocalypse because I
think we talked about it before we
started recording and I think it was
Jamie wheal that Delia nated those three
words apocalypse Armageddon and can't
remember the last one but it'll probably
come to me and he talked about
apocalypse being at the unveiling and
that feels very relevant in the context
of the lockdown in the context of Kovach
because it seems to be revealing all of
the stress points of the cultures and
also individually in Locke to helm how
good are your primary relationships how
good you are spending time with yourself
how how strong how much trust do you
have in your immediate environment all
of these factors which I think you're
going to become more and more like I
think you probably share a similar sense
that we're actually only at the
beginning
of this yeah process rather than yeah
whatever happens this was a shock to a
system that is now seemingly unraveling
moment by moment and is going to
continue to do so yeah yeah yeah and so
the way that I've lived in response to
that is to try to extract myself as much
as I can from the system so that as it
gets shocked and unravels I don't it
doesn't destroy me I voluntarily destroy
myself so that it can't hurt me in the
way that it could you know like I've
been doing these radio interviews and
and it's so weird how they work there
five or ten minutes long and but they
just process you you just kind of are
like cattle you're just being put
through this information harvesting
machine the story harvesting machine and
um some of the some of the people that
do it are very good at making you feel
comfortable but I know that you really
care because I know you and it feels and
and but in going through that process
with all these like news stories I start
to like lose track of who I am or I
start to lose track of my perspective
because I know that I know that they
want something in particular like that
New York Times article we talked about a
lot of different stuff we talked for
over three hours I talked for over three
hours with Ellen the journalist and I
knew before that process started I knew
during I knew after there was a
particular story that she had in mind
and it wasn't about why you would do a
solitary retreat or what maple is what
the monastic Academy is and what it
stands for what I was trying to achieve
you know it was a different kind of
story that she wanted and I appreciate
being in a space where like I can kind
of just speak what's true for me
instead of having to deal with what I X
what I think that you want me to say mmm
which i think is really common in our
media in the mainstream media sphere now
I know yeah and also there's the the
thing that the more that you tell the
story if you're telling it to like 10
different media outlets you get to learn
pretty quickly what are the key bits
that they want to hear and then you
start early then you start delivering a
story that hits those particular yeah oh
yeah yeah you see it's like fractal
metaprogramming right it just goes all
the way down the stack so that I then
become a tool of this kind of collective
intelligence oh it's very weird and I I
it's I don't know how people like get
famous and then after they get actually
famous they're like actually Fame is not
really what I thought it would be like
having just a little bit of exposure now
like just a very very very very tiny
amount like being the New York Times and
talk it's not that it's not good it's
not conducive to happiness hmm it's not
satisfying is that because of that and
that process that you were just talking
about like effectively yourself your
story starts becoming externalized in
some way yeah yeah you the more
attention you're having on you the more
kind of representations of your story
that are being produced the more it
starts to collapse the experience that
you've had into a exactly narrative and
it's not your narrative it's the
narrative that the betrayal no that's
right exactly and it's fucked up and so
yeah it's it's really messed up yeah I
think that's exactly well set yeah well
said I've never really considered it
like that but just hearing your
description of it really fits like in a
way wow that there's also this sort of
sense of you know the is it Native
Americans who believe that if you're
photographing a part of your your soul
was captured yeah there's something true
in that as a as an analogy yeah yeah
well sir I i sat my retreat for the
exact same duration as my friend
time was my friend Peter Park who lives
here at the monastery with me a
wonderful human being and obviously he
didn't happen York Times article written
about him he hasn't had to deal with all
this or had this opportunity and you how
you look at it
and I think he's happier and I think
that his retreat is more sacred its
maintaining its sacredness relative to
me there it's being held sacrosanct it's
being protected in a way that mine now
is out of my hands in a very confusing
way perhaps unlike anybody who's ever
sat a silent retreat in the history of
the planet it occurs to me you know like
I don't know that anybody's ever come
out of a set retreat and then had a New
York Times or had and a planetary
information system harvest their story
for the entertainment of the populace
that's a fascinating idea right you
might have had the most newsworthy
silent retreat that there have been yeah
yeah yeah which probably just shows us
how narcissistic everybody is yeah yeah
especially if you're right that it's
actually a reflection of ourselves that
we're looking for a new rather than
interested in you and your experience
yeah just sounds if if a lot of people
have sort of or if the interview so far
haven't really asked how it was for you
they're not really interested in for
that no I don't think I want to tell you
say you've had a few of these different
interviews what is the story that they
want to tell you yeah I mean so the that
I'm like Rip Van Winkle and I'm like
emerging into this completely changed
world and they want me to tell them how
I see the change they want me to tell
them what's been surprising about how
the world has changed so they want to
they want me to acknowledge I guess what
is what they went through or what what
shifts have taken place
probably in order to further consolidate
their vision of this being a really
significant time in history I really
like monumental epic oh yeah like you
know epic shifting event it's my
imagination but I haven't haven't
thought about it too deeply yet and and
do they know that your entire work
before now was effectively saying that
there will be local world-changing event
collapse unclear Laurie that's that's
the paradox as well is that all of these
people are like oh wow there's a really
good story here and they're pushing it
into a narrative that they understand
and they think their viewers want but
actually the story itself is so much
more interesting than that here's a guy
who's gone as deeply as anyone into
understanding collapse and understanding
system dynamics and kind of effectively
came to the end of that inquiry I'm not
sure what happens next and I that's what
I find extraordinary as well as that I
was picking up something similar I
remember we talked I think was last year
at the emerge gathering and you were
sort of feeling the end of that inquiry
and I kind of I wasn't quite there but
then I had a series of experiences
certainly towards the beginning of this
year where I felt something similar he
met with Eric Weinstein who said almost
exactly the same thing he kind of was
looking around and saying I feel like
the system has crystallized and it's
effectively dead and I was like yeah
that feels right of the inquiry that
rebel wisdom has been on since the
beginning and in Corey that you've been
on this sort of sense of what's new and
emerging and sensing actually I'm not
sure what it is I mean something else is
gonna happen and then the pandemic and
the sort of second and third-order
consequence so like okay that was the
thing that was that was coming mmm do
you feel like your inquiry has been
revitalized by kovaydin value well yes
yeah very much so like this is in a sort
of
clichéd these are the times that we've
been waiting for kind of kind of way
yeah and also yeah feeling really like I
feel like and maybe you feel the same
with with emerge I feel like the the
films that we put out over the last two
or three years on rebel wisdom all of so
much of what's happening now within
those films like I want to just go
through the back catalogue and grab all
of these kind of amazing because
effectively saying okay these are the
deep forces that are at work the Jordan
rules the daniel trachtenberg is the
nora Bateson's and say look we this was
going something like this was going to
happen and this is likely to only be the
beginning of this process because it's
something we've done a series of events
since the beginning of the pandemic
about resilience and sense making sense
making is a form of resilience oh yes
why if something is happening being able
to understand okay what are the tectonic
plates that our ship is not being
overwhelmed by the by the impact of
what's going on it's such a crucial
thing yeah and in the rebel wisdom
community in amongst our members I
remember the very first zoom call that
we had after after the pandemic sort of
really kicked in most people on the call
not all but most were actually saying
breathing kind of sigh of relief it's
like and yes I know what's going on I
feel that I'm waiting for something like
this Wow huh yeah I've actually heard
the the sense of what you just said
echoed by a lot of folks that I've
spoken with since I've left retreat you
know you know that are in our kind of
extended network that they feel like
yeah that
what we've been training for in a sense
this is what we've been preparing for
that we're kind of now is the time to
show up in a way that we've been saying
we're gonna need to show up in yeah yeah
I don't want it to get to
self-congratulatory because I think
there are things that we also need to do
as a community to read I think wow yeah
yeah no go back to crying I don't know
maybe that's another conversation but I
feel I feel that just more generally I
don't think I don't think we have the
the structures or the coherence to
respond as meaningfully as I think we
should or as we need to
yeah and that was actually my sense when
I heard people say this it's just like
oh interesting so the echo chamber is
still alive hmm and maybe even more more
echo II might might I mean so what two
things that come up for me one is one of
the impacts of I think both my retreat
and coming to the end of this inquiry
have been something that Zack Stein said
in one of our last conversations he said
you know game a game B that's all fine
but the real game is the people you
spend time with the real game is who you
live with and how you treat them and
something about the end of this inquiry
has just left me in that place where I'm
just like oh great so I've had all these
philosophical conversations that have
like seriously reordered my
consciousness and my the way I see
things how does that actually help me
love the people I'm with how does that
actually help me move in the world in a
way that I can be proud of actually does
it and for me going forward I think that
really has to be the litmus test like
I'm I'm not willing to have
conversations that are actually abstract
to the point where they don't impact
that directly
and and what's interesting is that I
think those conversations actually can
look quite abstract the conversations
that help us love because so much of
what keeps us that prevents us from
loving is the kind of philosophical
ontological and epistemological systems
that we naively participate in like
materialism and humanism and liberalism
and so it's so it's a funny position of
being because even as I've been on these
radio shows they introduced me often as
a full as an online philosopher which is
the worst
title I think that you could be but are
the most easily characterized title I
think you could be given easily
satirized yeah exactly and and you know
these conversations seem very
philosophical but I think they're
actually more eminent than just about
anything else we can talk about because
they are the lens through which we view
everything else we could talk about and
so that's one of the things that I'm
most interested is I think that just
like there's an opportunity now to build
kind of new social structures and new
information since making structures
there's also an opportunity to reinvent
the cosmos to break out of materialism
to break out of humanism and find
ourselves again in a world that's in
sold that it's meaningful and it calls
us forth into a sense of divine duty and
that is necessary I think if we're
actually gonna thread the eye of the
needle in the years to come
I don't think it's not even I don't
think it's even worth doing it if we
can't really can that or awaken that
sense that meaningful message sacredness
you documented that journey with the
emerge podcast and you really you you
made a live exploration and recorded
your your exploration to a lot of these
topics I guess one of the things is if
people want to kind of retrace your
steps which one which
particular conversations would you
suggest they listen to yeah I probably I
would recommend the three conversations
djembe and L who wrote the deep
adaptation paper Vinay Gupta who well
this is Vinay Gupta you have to listen
to it and then sorry you for all the
most recent conversation that gives the
kind of arc where I was reckoning
finally completely with the basically
becoming convinced having attained to
the conviction about collapse and then
deciding to move back to maple to accord
with that conviction and then the
conversation with soryu I think places
the aspiration for awakening spiritual
enlightenment in in light of and in
terms of this what time it is on the
planet and so that I think gives it
Kenneth
nice nutshell of my my recent journey
yeah yeah and I guess my we actually
recorded a conversation about collapse
you have you me and Josh fields oh yeah
and in that I think I for a long time
I've I've got sort of one foot in the
Jordan Pederson camp in particular like
wearing one of the best times to be
alive we we shouldn't be we have to be
grateful for the miracle of civilization
and holding that peace alongside a lot
of the most brilliant people I'm
speaking to talking about self
terminating systems and being persuaded
by that at the same time but not I never
went into it as fully as you did or
maybe Josh did and my my sense was
holding all of these different pieces
but at the beginning of the pandemic for
me that possibility space really kind of
collapse down to ok the systems thinkers
and the the collapse ologists I think
they as you saw this start to cascade
you saw all the fragilities become clear
for me it kind of closing yeah all of
these impossibilities it really started
to close the space in terms of what's
really going on and what
who was sort of seeing who had the most
complete vision of what the kind of
societal fragilities were so that's part
of my my journey whether it was like oh
actually now okay I I feel like I feel
like I held a lot of those
impossibilities and now it sort of
become a little bit more clear as to
which one was true and which one wasn't
and specifically it was the systems
theorists and the people who were really
talking about systems for jodean
collapse but you felt we're more yeah
yeah yeah and and the also the the
nature of a self terminating system
especially just looking at the bit that
I'm primarily focused on which is the
the sense making system and conveying
how even that even happened was then
dragged into this sort of polarization
spiral of how do we know what is true
everything being weaponized from health
advice to kind of alternative narratives
to just just realizing oh my god we have
no way of determining what is true we're
having all of these all of these factors
that we'd kind of were aware of the sort
of how sticky something is how much it's
sort of reliant on outrage and limbic
hijack and all of those kind of the the
ecosystem of social media and and then
realizing wow even-even Cove it is now
becoming a culture war issue told that
look that for me is oh my god
was was something I didn't I didn't
expect because that didn't really happen
in the UK so much the UK generally the
centre has held to some to a much
greater degree than it has in the States
I mean Europe I'd say to so to a degree
you can argue that that may have changed
into a different like I think we may be
in a different space now with the with
the riots and with the these other kind
of narratives that are now kind of going
to war with each other but that feels
like a significant shift from where we
were before but I guess that yeah yeah
yeah and I think I've been you know
slowly
chin up and it's been interesting to
watch myself try to make sense of how of
all this and who I turned towards right
and it's primarily Daniel Shakti Berger
Jordan Hall nor Bateson and the thing
that I hear especially Jordan and Daniel
warning about is you know Daniel I think
said only 1% of warfare is kinetic and
just really seeing I think if there's
one one thing coming out of retreat that
became clear to me was just how much our
way of seeing the world is colored by
the information ecosystem we participate
in like as soon as I I went back in it
was like I was in a different world
I just like all of a sudden poof I'm in
a world of cultural warfare and you know
various kinds of memetic conflicts and
it's like that's not real but I think
it's really important that we both
realize that that's not real and that we
can periodically relieve ourselves from
having to participate in it completely I
think one of the things that I was
looking at in my retreat was that this
you know one of the fundamental like
laws of consciousness is what you
attuned to in your perception gets
amplified regardless of what it is right
so if you if you have pain in your leg
and your attention just falls into that
your whole world can become pain if you
have pleasure well-being arising in your
body and you learn how to pay attention
to that skillfully your whole world can
become pleasure and well-being and so
coming out of retreat I just felt a lot
more careful about what I allow to
occupy my attention in terms of the
world that it will then create for me
that I will then you know spread
to others in my network and in my world
and so I appreciate Daniel in particular
his caution around this just going his
invitation just go slowly don't collapse
into a perspective yet like we are in a
liminal space and it's appropriate to be
liminal yeah yeah likewise I think of
all yea daniel has a real uncanny skill
to be able to speak to he's able to
speak without activating anyone immune
anyone's immune system yeah which is
which is what I'm kind of realizing is
actually the most the most important
thing well is to not activate the immune
system of either right or left yeah long
enough that people can actually hear
what you're trying to say rather than
immediately collapse into this this is
the this is the primary thing is that in
every single area now it's like which
side are you on
and yeah not interested in oh my god in
anything beyond that just like I'm
waiting for you to signal which side
you're on
whether that's and there's so many
topics and they're so mean totally this
is why it was it was so scary to talk to
the New York Times coming out of retreat
cuz I had no III knew that the cultural
battlegrounds had shifted because of
kovat and that there are things that I
you know wasn't supposed to say and
things that I like was supposed to say
according to certain ideologies but I
had no idea what it was right so I found
myself being very cautious in the way
that I expressed myself
and it's like what you say like even
coming out I noticed that I was like and
somebody would say something like oh you
know the Republicans they're not they're
trying to get us not to wear masks and I
was like ok great so I now know that
that is that ideological line it's drawn
there very good there's some continuity
that makes sense the Republicans would
do that
and then some liberals believe that
5-bit kovat is caused by 5g I'm just
like what is happening here is even
going on but you know yeah but but there
are but there are paradoxes even within
that which is on a classic kind of Big
Five personality Republicans are more
interested in sanctity like the fact
that it actually has become a signifier
on the right to not care about covert or
to be more in favor of lifting lock down
is is interesting you wouldn't
necessarily have expected that actually
there's more there's more antipathy
towards disease on the right than there
is on the left like that's that's one of
the kind of signifiers but it's mmm it's
extraordinary like the whole thing is
being shifted in in real time
totally and depending on what key
figures say well yeah and so I I find
myself pretty ambivalent about about
whether to and to what degree to try to
piece it all together again
I imagine I wouldn't have felt that way
if I had been there through the the
accelerating deconstruction
reconstruction like if I had been
participating in it I probably would
have felt more like included or
something but I just I can't there's a
part of me that can't find a reason to
care too much about it that sounds
healthy
yeah I wonder I don't know it's an open
question for me yeah I mean I guess the
other question is how how was the
retreat like 75 grade yeah retreat with
meditation and yeah I mean it's funny
how nobody asked me about how their tree
was you're one of the first people owned
outside of my community here yeah so it
was 75 days I was in silence in a cabin
on the land here at the monastic Academy
the captain has no electricity
running water just propane heating and
it's pretty small you know enough space
for a bed a meditation cushion and like
a yoga mat basically and I went in when
the snow was you know up to my waist
just about here in northern Vermont and
I came out in you know beautiful spring
day and in that dirt in those 75 days
it's pretty simple you know it's not
that exciting it's kind of like a very
boring version of the movie Groundhog
Day I just got up meditated for two
hours you had some tea meditated for two
hours went for a walk
meditated for two hours I had lunch went
for a longer walk meditated for two
hours not with the teacher for five or
ten minutes meditate for two hours go to
sleep with exercise and you know crying
and laughing and connecting with the
birds between all that interspersed in
there yeah so it's pretty pretty simple
and how was your inner experience during
it well so I it was definitely the best
experience I've had in my life who say
that you know without a doubt is the
most well I can even really say why it
was the best experience of my life but I
I know that it was the inner experience
you know if you've ever done any kind of
retreat like this it contained
everything or the whole spectrum of what
the human being I think is capable of
experiencing an intense grief
unbelievable joy you know boredom kind
of love hatred self-hatred freedom tons
of suffering 75 days is a long time so
you can pack a lot in there and I was
mostly exploring this kind of meditation
called the jhanas like exploring the
genres which are states of basically
altered states of states of
consciousness in the Buddhist tradition
which I could explore more with you if
that's interesting and then spend a lot
of time exploring the soul making Dharma
which I've talked about with the creator
of it Rob for Bay on the show Robert
they actually just passed away while I
was on retreat and so yeah that's what I
spent most of my time doing and of
course inevitably you think about things
and you deal with what comes up and it's
it's an incredibly rich experience and
it's also kind of ineffable I imagine in
the same way that a lot of folks
experiences quarantine and lockdown is
you know you can kind of say like what
it is that you did but the the psychic
territory that you move through is so
intimate that you really can't talk
about it at least not adequately and so
I and so yeah it's like that it's like
that yeah oh you also managed somehow to
get covered while you were so it one of
the people who came to the last retreat
before we kind of were gonna we walked
down the center for the center was
locked down I think they came from
Boston and this was you know early March
so before shit had really hit the fan I
think they brought it and it just spread
like nothing I've ever seen around this
community I think almost everybody got
it and then about a week and a half or
two weeks later I got it somehow yeah
it's cool I could I could because I was
meditating I could watch it like from
from birth to death very closely and I
said see what it did to my body and also
see what my mind tried to do with it hmm
at the end of this process if you've got
any insight or thoughts into what you
want to do with emerge you're feeling
called to to make any more podcasts or
any more conversations I will definitely
have more podcasts more conversations I
think I need to sync up a little bit
with the collective before I start
deciding what that's gonna look like but
where I'm feeling drawn right now is
into actually like longer form and rarer
conversations so doing like really deep
dives with folks about particular topics
and so getting getting even more
esoteric perhaps but that's just feels
like that's where I'm drawn and
especially with the emergence of like
the stoah I think that that is doing a
lot of the work that I originally set
out to do with emerge and so it's ended
with rebel wisdom you know I'm just like
it's great when friends come and sort of
like take care of parts of the picture
so that you know you can just step back
and do the thing that's uniquely yours
so I think something like the more deep
dives longer form is maybe what's
uniquely mine yeah do you have a thought
of topics subjects or people hmm
I have some thoughts but I haven't had
it sorted all out yet I'm definitely
gonna do a long series with Zach's Tina
he lives nearby and we've been spending
time together I think there's a lot that
he has to share that hasn't yet made it
onto podcasts or media appearances that
he's made so that's certainly gonna
happen don't know beyond that yeah
what's been the most surprising thing
since you've come out
I think like how much easier it is for
me to love the people I'm around yeah I
think both because of covent maybe but
also because of my practice like a lot
of the ways that I've kept myself from
caring about and loving the people that
are just here in this community have
fallen away and it feels just really
effortless to love them and it's
wonderful and I was surprised because
usually when you kind of like feel all
lovey when you come off of a retreat
that fades pretty quick you know because
people are complicated but it's it's
stuck around so far so I'm really
surprised about that hmm so you're still
in the honeymoon period after the baby I
mean it doesn't feel like it it feels
like I got like just thrown back out
into the wilds you know with them just
the my life after the retreat and that's
partly why I'm surprised that this part
has maintained it's because I actually
have like lost my shit in a lot of
respects pretty quickly after their
treatment I felt felt like a good point
too close to the green yeah thank you
David been a pleasure to speak with you
yeah you too Daniel it's been yeah
really good too yeah hear what you have
come back with and the yeah the insight
not only the insight that you got from
from the the retreat but also the
insight that I feel that it's given you
into the kind of the dynamics of the
media and the dynamics of sort of the
system that you're re-entering mmm I
think it's really really fascinating as
well and maybe maybe you're able to see
it more clearly because you've sort of
cleaned your mire cleared your mind a
little bit on the on the retreat so
there for coming out there's more of a
like handbrake turn of whoa what yeah
and it's also helped helps to speak with
somebody like yourself I think you
you've many of what much of what I've
said I
did not know I knew until you asked the
question so appreciate you calling it
forth that's a real conversation rebel
wisdom was set up to make sense of the
world at a deeper level than the
mainstream media it was built for these
times of crisis and change which is why
we want to do what we can to meet the
challenge of the times more films and
also for our rebel wisdom members weekly
sense-making calls with our amazing
interviewees and also we're introducing
the wisdom gym a place to practice some
of the skills that we've talked about on
the channel thanks for watching and see
you soon
[Music]